<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ above all exalted, as in justification so in sanctification. Wherein severall passages in Dr. Crisps sermons are answered. / Delivered in a sermon at Rye, in the county of Sussex: by John Benbrigge minister of Gods Word at Ashburnham, in the same county:.</title>
            <author>Benbrigge, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76380</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E300_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200254</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861060</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861060</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113188</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76380)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113188)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 49:E300[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ above all exalted, as in justification so in sanctification. Wherein severall passages in Dr. Crisps sermons are answered. / Delivered in a sermon at Rye, in the county of Sussex: by John Benbrigge minister of Gods Word at Ashburnham, in the same county:.</title>
                  <author>Benbrigge, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Stafford, and are to be sold at his house in Brides Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Crisp, Tobias.  Christ alone exalted.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7bre 9th" [i.e. September? 9th; bound with items from September, but Thomason catalogue lists under October].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Crisp, Tobias, 1600-1643. --  Christ alone exalted --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians III, 7-10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113188:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRIST ABOVE ALL EXALTED, AS IN JVSTIFICATION SO IN SANCTIFICATION.</p>
            <p>Where in ſeverall Paſſages in D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. CRISPS Sermons are Anſwered.</p>
            <p>Delivered in a SERMON at RYE, in the County of <hi>Suſſex:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JOHN BENBRIGGE Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Aſhburnham,</hi> in the ſame County:</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 COR. 1.30.</bibl>
               <p>But you are of him in Chriſt Jeſus, who of God is made unto us, Wiſdome and Righteouſneſſe, and Sanctification and Redemption.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for <hi>John Stafford,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Houſe in Brides Church-yard 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113188:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113188:2"/>
            <head>TO MY WORTHY AVNT Miſtreſſe SARAH NOWELL.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <list>
                  <item>All Peace <hi>Externall,</hi> Amen.</item>
                  <item>All Peace <hi>Eternall,</hi> Amen.</item>
                  <item>All Peace <hi>Internall,</hi> Amen.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Endeared Aunt:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HOM I love not onely in the Fleſh, but alſo and eſpecially in the Truth, and not I onely, but alſo all they that have known the truth, for the thuth's ſake, which dwelleth in us, and ſhall be with us for ever.
<note place="margin">2 John 1, 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Peter's <hi>Watch-word muſt never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, whilſt our warfare lasteth;</hi> Be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> be vigilant <hi>(ſaith he) and his reaſon is)</hi> Becauſe your adverſary the devil, as a roaring Lyon walketh about, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom he may devour; <hi>and as the world drawes nearer to an end, ſo he mends his pace, and bestirs himſelfe the more, becauſe his time growes ſhorter;
<note place="margin">Revel. 12.12. 1 Cor. 10.11. Eph. 5.15, 16. 17, 18.</note> wherefore we (on whom the ends of the world are come more neere) ought to walke more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly, both in ſobriety and watchfulneſſe for new he makes more uſe of his ſeverall turns and fetches then heretofore; that phraſe of walking or going about, implies he hath many of them; and truly I think the world never ſaw more of them in one age, then may be ſeene in ours: As an old ſouldier hath many ſtratagems to circumvent his enemie, and ſuch as ſuit beſt with time, place
<pb facs="tcp:113188:3"/>and power, he puts in execution to make way for an aſſault; like politick ſtratagems and engines hath the ſpirituall adverſary of our ſoules and ſalvation, to ſet upon us and undoe us. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle cals them ſometimes his devices, at other times his wiles: his devices are fine devices,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.11. 1 pheſ. 6.11.</note> ſpun out in a curious thred; his wiles are ſubtill for cunning; both are one, though the letters of the words differ, yet their ſenſe fully agrees; for his wiles are fine devices, and his devices ſultill wiles: This latter word, as it is in the Originall,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> duly conſidered, opens unto us the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of both, ſhewing where in this his fine cunning doth chiefly lye, namely, in his marſhalling of thoſe his ſubtill devices, that is, the method he uſeth and followeth in acting them. For firſt, he labours to prevent the planting of grace in the heart, and if he faile of his project therein, then he in the next place, caſts about to hinder the growth of grace in heart and life: Repentance, faith and obedience are the totall of Chriſtianity, beyond which we have nothing to do or profeſſe; in theſe three are ſummed up all the Prophets and Apostles, and the devil ſeeks as much to hinder, as all they doe to further them: to prevent the implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of grace, he ſeeks to keep them from repentance; which if he cannot doe, then to ſtarve grace, that it may have no ſuste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, he endeavours to overthrow their faith and obedience; before a man (acted by ſaving grace) ſets himſelfe to repent, all his work is to ſtrengthen his faith, that is, to make him beleeve he is in a goad and ſafe condition, though indeed he be nothing leſſe, and this is to keep him from repenting, and when he ſees the man will repent (for the grace of God conſtraines him thereto) then he wheels about, and to weaken his faith, he ſets in order before him all his ſinnes, which before he hid from his eyes, yea, he aggravates them as much as he can, both for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and meaſure, for quality, quantity and number, deſirous to bring him to conceive them greater then can be pardoned; but when he finds this his device frustrated by the ſoules cleaving
<pb facs="tcp:113188:3"/>to, and laying hold on Gods free grace in Chriſt, juſtifying and acquitting him from the guilt of all his ſinnes; then his laſt piece of policy is to kinder his ſanctification, and to lay ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-blocks in his way of new obedience, that he may fall him into actuall tranſgreſſions, thereby to diſhonour God, wound his owne conſcience, and diſhearten others from walking godly, righteouſly and ſoberly in this preſent world; many are the rubs he layes in this ſoules courſe of Christianity, but none of the leaſt are the totall casting away of the law, as unuſefull, and not belonging to him; and the unfruitfulneſſe of duty to the doer thereof in any kind: Theſe flones (with their like) he had caſt in the wayes of Gods people heretofore, but by the power of Chriſts ſpirit in ſome of his worthies, they were removed, and have laine hid, till of late, Satan finding an opportunity, hath againe tumbled them in: And herein his cunning craftineſſe appeares yet greater (to ſuch as ſeriouſly obſerve things with a ſpirituall eye) that he carries his matters ſo ſlyly, as he gets ſome of his knowne enemies to countenance and defend them, and ſo to help and fight for him; like as the Papiſts (taught in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of him) have carried on their fine devices ſo wilily, as to delude ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Protestants, their knowne and ſworne adverſaries ſo farre as to make them take part with him againſt their owne Chriſt, his Gospell and ſervants, their Brethren; is not this Satans Master-piece, to bring Gods ſervants to fight againſt him, to make good men with stand good works? Yet this is no new matter; for he got once into</hi> Peter's <hi>mouth, and made him ſpeak againſt Christs doing that good work of our ſalvation:</hi> Peter <hi>indeed ſpake out of love to Chriſt, and he meant to ſave Chriſt, as he thought; but the truth is, he ſpake then he knew not what: In like manner thoſe good ſoules, who neglect ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to extoll justification, who reject the law, casting it behind their backs, as of no uſe, to advance the Gospell, who heat downe all duty of a true beleever, as no way beneficiall to
<pb facs="tcp:113188:4"/>him to exalt Chriſt; I beare them record, that they have a zeale of God, but not according to knowledge; they under stand no more what they ſay then</hi> Peter <hi>did, when Chriſt ſaid to him,</hi> get thee behind me Satan; <hi>for the Law is as much Chriſt's as the Gospell, and Gods free grace in Chriſt, is as much ſeene and magnified in our Sanctification as our Justification; he gave Chriſt for both, and Chriſt dyed for both; they therefore that beat downe the Law, throw downe Christs Scepter, and lay his honour in the duſt; doth not our preſent dayly experience ſhew what will become of a Kingdome, if the lawes thereof be taken away? and they which extoll Gods onely free grace in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, clip Gods Coyne, our onely riches; they ſet up but half a Chriſt, &amp; ſo by halving him, they whittle him to nothing;</hi> Paul <hi>knew this very well; if his Epistles be ſeriouſly ſcanned, if the matter of them be ſifted well into the two maine parts thereof, justification and ſanctification by Chriſt Jeſus, and each part weighed by it ſelfe, the greateſt quantity of them would be in ſanctifications ſcale. True indeed, in his Epistle to the Romans and Galatians, he is much on free grace in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, againſt Jewiſh confidence in Phariſaicall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances; but in thoſe and in all his other Epistles, he is as much and ſometimes more inſisting on Gods free grace in ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, and exhorting thereunto, againſt that looſneſſe and careleſneſſe of walking, which he ſaw in many Chriſtians; truely to me his greateſt care ſeems to be for the maintainance of good works, both in himſelfe and others: In others, as appeares by</hi> Titus 3.8. <hi>and many other places; in himſelf,</hi> Rom. 7. <hi>ch. (if there were no more teſtimonies) makes it evident; now his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample ſhould herein be a leading rule to us Miniſters his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, both for practice to our ſelves, and for doctrine unto others; wherefore having (as you know) yeelded to importunity to ſpeak a word of exhortation to my native Towne, the holy ſpirit directed me to pitch on ſuch a portion of Scripture, as
<pb facs="tcp:113188:4"/>led me to the maintainance of ſanctification, and ſetting forth of the neceſſity of Gods free grace in Chriſt therefore, to be as great as in matter of juſtification; a poynt directly croſſing thoſe miſhapen opinions of thoſe new-faſhioned Chriſtians (for ſo they be to us) that are called Antinomians; and therefore a poynt moſt fit for</hi> Rye, <hi>wherein many of that ſect were voted to be, by reaſon of thoſe frequent, loud and bitter exclamations againſt them, by name in the Pulpit, joyned with as earneſt and vehement exhortations to take heed of them, and dehortations from their ſociety, as moſt dangerous infectious perſons. I thought now with my ſelf, being to come into that place, it would be my duty to fight againſt the doctrine, as others had done againſt the name of the Antinomians; and ſo I did, and I hope my labour was not in vaine to the Auditory, I am ſure it is not in vaine in the Lords account, whoſe truth it was that I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and I delivered it as his and none of mine; and would not a man conceive this would have been very acceptable to him who ſeems ſuch a profeſſed enemy to the Antinomians? but the contrary appeared to the weakeſt of his Auditors: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon who can but think that either he miſtooke the perſons he ſo called, or that he did not underſtand what the Lord delivered by me: for mine owne part, I muſt needs ſay, it ſeems to me as cleere as the Sunne at noon-day, that he hath miſtaken both them &amp; me, &amp; ſo abuſed both, with that ſcandalous name of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomian; the Lord open his eyes to ſee the great wrong he hath done me and them hereby, that he may repent thereof, and have his pardon ſealed before he goe hence: in the meane time, it is more then probable, that he which durſt ſnarle at the truth of Chriſt before my face, will behind my back take more liberty to himſelfe to let the reines looſe to his unruly tongue (a fit inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter to his paſſionate mind) both to bark louder and bite dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, by altering the phraſe and corrupting the ſenſe of my words; wherefore I thought it neceſſary in Chriſtian wiſdome, by way
<pb facs="tcp:113188:5"/>(if not of prevention, yet) of anſwering to ſuch envious and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious dealing, to communicate the notes of my diſcourſe under mine own hand; and into whoſe hand could I more fitly put them then into yours? not only in regard of the outward relation, I have to you, but alſo becauſe you have been accuſed falſly, as farre as I can conceive, to be one of them that are looked at as Antinomians; ſo that mine intent in publiſhing this my labour under your name, is not ſo much to manifeſt my due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects of you, as to let the credulous world (which is ready to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace any reports that may ſcandalize the ſervants of Chriſt) ſee how it hath been miſ-informed concerning you and ſuch others, as with you, lye at this preſent clouded with that black asperſion of Antinomianiſme, for instead of crying downe the Law, Sanctification and Duty, I found you upon diligent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, both in opinion and practice, chiefe pillars thereof. The Lord comfort your hearts more and more with his free grace, and ſtabliſh you in every good word and work,
<note place="margin">2 Thel. 2.17. 2 Cor. 7.1.</note> that you may thereby perfect holineſſe in his feare here, and hereafter be perfected in happineſſe,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your younger Brother in Chriſt, and affectionate Nephew in the Fleſh, JOHN BENBRIGGE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113188:5"/>
            <head>CHRIST ABOVE ALL EXALTED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PHILIPPIANS 3.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>7.</bibl> But what things were gaine to me, thoſe I counted loſſe for Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>8.</bibl> Yea doubtleſſe, and I count all things but loſſe for the excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord; for whom I have ſuffered the loſſe of all things, and doe count them but dung that I may win Chriſt,</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>9.</bibl> And be found in him: Not having mine owne righteouſneſſe, which is of the Law; but that which is through the Faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe which is of God by Faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>10</bibl> That I may know him, and the power of his Reſurrection, and the fellowſhip of his Sufferings, being made conformable unto his Death.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction_of_text">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe words we have <hi>Saul</hi> compared with <hi>Paul;</hi> the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles doth herein compare himſelf with himſelf, ſeting forth to us both what he was, and what he is; what he was when he was <hi>Saul,</hi> and what he is now he is <hi>Paul;</hi> what he was before Converſion, what he is ſince his Calling; and this deſcription of himſelfe then, and and now, is delineated by the difference of his judgement now and then: <hi>For men are according to their judgements, and in the ſight of the Al ſeeing eye, as theſe change and alter, ſo doe they to be carnall or ſpirituall;</hi> the Apoſtle in 1 Cor. 2.14, 15. doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh of other men (as he did of himſelfe) by their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of things: A carnall man judgeth carnally of all things, but a ſpirituall man ſpiritually. Thus carnall <hi>Saul</hi> had a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113188:6"/>opinion of things; he had an high eſteem of his owne righteouſneſſe, which was by the Law, his Phariſaicall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of duty, and of his Jewiſh priviledges; yea, theſe were his gaine, he did not onely eſteem of them, but alſo confide in them, he hoped to gaine Heaven by them; but as for Chriſt then, he was a poore Chriſt to him, worth nothing, yea worſe then nothing in his account then, and therefore he perſecuted then this diſpiſed Chriſt in his Members: But now he is ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Paul,</hi> he is quite of another mind; for now he looks at his owne righteouſneſſe, Phariſaicall works and fleſhly Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; yea, all things of this world as loſſe and dung, and poor Chriſt is now moſt rich, and the true, yea, onely gaine, and therefore he had loſt to himſelfe all things, that he might in their roome get Chriſt: When ſaving grace comes to a <hi>Saul,</hi> it enters in at the underſtanding firſt, that is, the everlaſting gate whereby the King of glory paſſeth in to the City of the heart;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 24 7. Mal. 4.2. Rom. 13.12. 2 Pet. 1.9.19.</note> he therefore is called a Sunne, and that is called light; becauſe by their light a man ſeeth more into things, more of them then he did before they came into him: He was before like a blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded man, that could ſee no more then a ſeem of things, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and falſe opinions ſo bemiſted him, as he could not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne aright of them: But when the day-ſtarre ariſeth in the darke place, his mind, then as he hath other eyes, ſo he ſees things otherwiſe; he finds that he was much miſtaken in things when he called loſſe gaine, and gaine loſſe; wherefore now he alters his Opinion, and accounts things as they are, loſſe ſhall be loſſe, and gaine, gaine onely to him. Is not this moſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in our Apoſtle? did not there fall off as thick as great ſcales from the eyes of his ſoule,
<note place="margin">Acts 9.18.</note> as from them of his body, when Chriſt Jeſus took poſſeſſion of him? Yea doubtleſſe; and hence it was that he changed his opinion of all things; and by decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this alteration, he cleerly tels us, he is not now the ſame man he was; as much difference between him then, and him now, as is between a <hi>Saul</hi> and a <hi>Paul,</hi> who are no more like one another then black and white; direct oppoſites, as loſſe is to gaine, and gaine to loſſe.</p>
               <p>A great change indeed; ſo great as himſelfe thought would ſeem a Paradox to the men of this world, his former Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113188:6"/>and brethren in affection; hence it is (as may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) that he repeats it over and againe; he would have them beleeve, it is certainly true there is ſuch an alteration of and in him; and to work it into them, comes upon them in a gradation, each ſtep being a preventive Anſwer to an Objection they might make.</p>
               <p>For in the ſeventh Verſe having ſhewne them the things which he accounted loſſe for Chriſt, the things that were gaine to him, his performances and priviledges, mentioned in the fifth and ſixth Verſes: They might have Objected, what, is this ſuch a matter? they are but ſome things thy judgement is alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, in compariſon of this Chriſt thou talkeſt of; to prevent their ſaying thus to him, in the eighth Verſe he ſaith to them, <hi>Yea doubtleſſe, I account all things loſſe for Chriſt:</hi> To whom they might reply; Thou doeſt ſay ſo <hi>Paul,</hi> but thou wilt not doe ſo; Yea, but I have done ſo already, is his returne: Hereto they might Object; It may be <hi>Paul</hi> thou haſt done ſo once, but thou wilt learne more wit then to doe ſo againe: Nay, ſaith he, for even now at this preſent time I doe ſo undervalue all things in compariſon of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord: I but <hi>Paul,</hi> might they ſay, why doeſt thou ſo prize Chriſt above all? He anſwers them, <hi>that I may win Chriſt:</hi> And what good can Chriſt doe thee when thou haſt him? why deſireſt thou Chriſt ſo much? He gives them and us two reaſons of his eſteem and deſire of Chriſt above all, in the two Verſes following; in the ninth Verſe, his reaſon is, <hi>that he might be justified in God's ſight;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal: 143.2. Rom. 3.22.</note> 
                  <hi>for in his ſight no fleſh ſhall be juſtified in his owne righteouſneſſe:</hi> He would not therefore for a world that God ſhould come to Judgement, and find him in his owne righteouſneſſe, and out of Chriſt and Chriſts righteouſneſſe, which is by Faith applied to us. And in the tenth Verſe, his ſecond motive to ſet up and ſeek Chriſt above all, was his ſanctification, and therefore he ſaith, <hi>that I may know him:</hi> Know him? might they ſay, what doeſt thou not know Chriſt, <hi>Paul?</hi> Why? we know Chriſt: I but my meaning is (ſaith the Apoſtle) not ſuch a knowledge as yours is; alas, it is not an hiſtoricall knowledge of him in mine head that I would have, but an experimentall knowledge of him in mine heart: I can talk of Chriſt as wellas you, but I would
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113188:7"/>feel Chriſt in me, and have Union and Communion with him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which you want: I would find in my heart and life the vertue of his Reſurrection, and a fellowſhip of his Death and Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. Now what meanes he by the vertue of Chriſt's Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but that which Divines call Vivification, that is, a quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning power therefrom to walk in newneſſe of life as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines himſelfe, Rom. 6.4. And what intends he by the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of Chriſt's Death and Sufferings, but that which we call Mortification, which is a dying to ſinne, as is evident from Rom. 6.5, 6, 7, 8. And what are Vivification and Mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but thoſe two parts of a Chriſtian which make up his San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification; for which Chriſt was as highly prized, and as ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly prized, and as carneſtly deſired by <hi>Paul,</hi> as for his Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
               <p>Thus have you briefly the ſcope and meaning of theſe foure Verſes read unto you; we will paſſe by the dividing of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their parts at this preſent, becauſe I have but a little time to ſpeak in, and much precious matter to ſpeak of; the Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that they naturally yeeld unto our conſideration are theſe five.</p>
               <p n="1">I. A man before Converſion doth alway confide in, and reſt on his performances of duty.</p>
               <p n="2">II. After converſion a mans judgement is altered concerning his owne righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Without Chriſt all things are but loſſe and dung.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Chriſt alone is the true gaine.</p>
               <p n="5">V. True ſaving grace (wherewith <hi>Paul</hi> was endued when he wrote theſe words of our Text) teacheth a poor ſoule to eſteem of Chriſt above all things, not onely for Juſtification but alſo for Sanctification.</p>
               <p>Of all theſe five I doe conceive this laſt moſt uſefull for this Congregation at this time, wherefore mine intent is (with Gods aſſiſtance) to confirme it unto you, and afterward make ſome uſe of it; which whilſt I doe, if you love Chriſt and prize him above all, you will yeeld me your patient attention.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="argument">
               <p>The Philoſophers often call man a little world in himſelfe; but Chriſtians know he is not ſuch an entire Common-wealth, as able to live of and by himſelfe; theſe ſay, if he depend on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113188:7"/>Chriſt for maintainance, he will ſoone breake and fall into ſo wretched a condition, as is farre worſe then a non-being: Chriſt therefore in whom are all the hid treaſures of God, muſt man repaire unto for ſupply of all his wants; but alas, he wants an heart to goe to him; he muſt be drawne by God the Father or elſe he will never come to Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 6.44. The l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gs of Free-wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l which the Papiſts and Arminians ſtand ſo much upon, will never be able to carry a ſoul ſo farre as Chriſt; there muſt be an inward principle of ſaving grace in the heart, to enable and direct us, or elſe we ſhall never truly deſire or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly ſind him to be ours. Indeed there may be ſome gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping after Chriſt, by the meanes of ſome common hear-ſay; N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions of Chriſt in theſa knowing times; yea, a ſoule may ſo ſtrongly deſire Chriſt, as to be willing to part with very much for him, and yet not truly deſire Chriſt, becauſe he may all this while ſeek Chriſt, not out of a love to Chriſt ſo much as to himſelfe: A Merchant that heares there is ſuch a rich Commodity, ſuch a precious Jewell to be had whereby he may greatly get, will part with much of his gold and ſilver for it, yet cannot he be ſaid to love that Commodity and Jewell ſo much as himſelfe, becauſe he ſeeks it onely for his owne gaine and profit by it:
<note place="margin">Mat. 13.45, 46.</note> So a man that heares of that precious Pearle of great price, Chriſt Jeſus, and that there is much to be gotten by him, no leſſe then ſalvation (which is a ſure enjoyment of all good, and a freedome from all evill) may be willing to bid pretty faire for Chriſt, and lay downe much for him, and yet not truly love Chriſt for Chriſt's owne ſake; he deſires but to ſerve himſelfe of Chriſt, and not that Chriſt ſhould be ſerved by him. Self-love will perſwade men to prize Chriſt highly for Juſtification, to get happineſſe by Chriſt, but onely ſaving grace teaches a ſoule to ſtt up Chriſt alſo above all for Saictifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, to get holineſſe, whereby he may ſerve Chriſt that hath ſaved him.</p>
               <p>The more cleerly to prove this truth, and to help your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories to carry the proofe thereof away with you, we will take it aſund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r into two parts, and ſhew you,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Why ſaving grace teacheth a poor ſoule to prize the Lord Jeſus above all things.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113188:8"/>
               <p n="2">2. Why ſaving grace makes the heart to eſteem Chriſt above not onely in Juſtification, but alſo in Sanctification.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <p>For the firſt there are three Reaſons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> The firſt ariſeth from the Operations of the holy Spirit, which worketh ſaving grace in the heart of any man; the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the Spirit in this way is two-fold, whence the Spirit hath in Scripture a double Epithite, and is called a Spirit of Bondage, and a Spirit of Adoption; theſe names of Bondage and Adoption, imply not a double Spirit, but a double and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Act of the ſame holy Spirit, which is wrought in every ſoule, when it is ſavingly wrought upon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. for then</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The holy Spirit doth diſcover to the ſoule its forlorne condition, in regard of ſinne, and the puniſhment therefore; it makes him ſenſible of the ſpirituall bondage under ſinue and ſatan; it makes him ſee and feele how he lyes bound and fette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hand and foot with the Cart-ropes of his iniquities; and withall the Spirit ſet before them the terrible countenance of an angry God, and ſo fils the ſoule with ſtinging and deep pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing feares, that the juſt Judge of Heaven and Earth will plague it according to its deſerts, both in the world and that to come; thus were <hi>Peters</hi> Auditors pricked to the heart, and as men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with the ſtrange and fearfull ſight of their ſinne and God's wrath, they cried out, <hi>Men and brethren what ſhall we doe?</hi> Acts 2.37. which outcry of ſuch ſoules is the greater, becauſe this Spirit ſhews them withall, the helpleſneſſe that is in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and the creature to remedy their preſent miſery; it makes them know the vanity and inſufficiency of all that is in them, or can come from them to work their deliverance: It blaſteth all their hopes from their owne righteouſneſſe, which before ſmelt as ſweet as a Roſe in their Noſtrils, but now ſavours worſe to them then the noyſome dunghill: In briefe, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit certifies them that all they have done, or whatever they can doe with the help of all the Creatures, cannot give them one lift out of their ſad condition; but here the good Spirit of God leaves not his children, for then they would fall into that Gulfe of deſpaire whereinto <hi>Came, Judas</hi> and ſuch like have fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, to their utter ruine.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The holy Spirit therefore having wounded the ſoule ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113188:8"/>deep as he pleaſeth, (for all are not broken in a like meaſure) he begins the cure thereof, by ſetting Chriſt before the ſoule, and laying open to it that fulneſſe of ſupplies which is in him; that he can, yea onely can help, that there is no Saviour but he, and withall lets him ſee that there is ſome hope of his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſt, yea that God hath given him the rich and full Chriſt, that by beleeving in him he might have everlaſting life, and hereupon the ſoule begins to long after Chriſt, all the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of it runne after Chriſt, prizing and ſeeking Chriſt above all; now doth the ſoule cry, Oh give me Chriſt, and take all! like as a man ready to be drowned, would give all the world if he had it, to ſave his life, and to find ſome ſafe footing; ſo a ſoule that is enlightned with the eye-ſalve of the holy Spirit, to ſee its ſinking condition with a glimpſe of hope of getting Chriſt, will gladly part with all it hath for this Pearl of great price any vertue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> A ſecond Reaſon why that ſoule that hath ſaving grace doth prize Chriſt above all, is drawne from the contrarieties that is between grace and ſin; theſe two are no better friends then fire and water, light and darkneſſe, hell and heaven, yea then God and the Devill, and their manner of working is as contrary and croſſe to each other; they walke oppoſite to one another, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing (if they can) the worke the other hath done: Sinne works the heart when it beares the ſway there, to preferre all things, yea every thing before Chriſt; but grace when it takes place in the heart, brings the heart to prize Chriſt above all things in generall, much more above every thing in particular. If we well weigh the matter, the firſt ſtep of our averſion from God, is an undervaluing of him; when <hi>Adam</hi> firſt fell off from God, did not he preferre himſelfe and his Wife before God? doth not the Lord plainly point out the cauſe of his peoples for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking him, to be an overweening conceit they had in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture above him, though that were indeed but a broken Ciſtern, and he a living Fountaine, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. Now the way of our ariſing muſt be contrary to that of our falling, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt ſtep of our converſion to our God, is an overvalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, that is, ſuch a high eſteem of him, as all things with their fulneſſe of beauty, are not thought comparable with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113188:9"/>him in a degree, that is, even leſſe then the leaſt: This is the work of that ſaving grace, Faith, 1 Pet. 2.7. As the former was of that vice infidelity; as this carries the heart off from God ſo this new byaſſes it, and turnes it round about to him againe; like as a skilfull School-maſter when a child is brought to him that hath been ill taught, is faine firſt to unteach him what he hath ill learned, and afterwards to ſet him forth: So ſaving grace when it comes to teach the heart (firſt doth <hi>dedoce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> then <hi>docere</hi>) firſt makes him unlearned what ſinne hath taught him falſe; and hence it is that ſuch a ſoule comes to prize the Lord Jeſus above all things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> The third and laſt cauſe hereof proceeds from that ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worth of Chriſt, which ſaving grace makes the heart ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of, by feeling thoſe unſpeakable benefits it is made partaker of by him, which are many; we will at this time but point out to you theſe ſix following.</p>
                  <p>One (which is the firſt and root of all the reſt) is Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation with God, Col. 1.21. Reconciliation is that gift of God's Free-grace in Chriſt, whereby ſuch as are ſtrangers and enemies become acquainted with God, and ſo have peace, joy and delight in him, and boldneſſe to him, Rom. 5.1, 2. and for the ground of emnity between God and them (which was ſinne that made the ſeperation and alienation, Iſa. 59.2. Col. 1.21.) is utterly taken away by Jeſus Chriſt his death, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſatisfied for ſinne, Eph. 2.16. So that now the poore ſoule inſtead of terrifying frownes, and heart-breaking threats and menaces, hath chearfull ſmiles and cordiall promiſes, good and comfortable words, Zach. 1.13. The Lord doth ſhine in love ſo clearly and abundantly on the ſoul, that it warmes him to the very heart, and makes him rejoyce with joy unſpeakable; this benefit by Chriſt may ſeem little in the eyes of ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but as we that have felt the bitterneſſe of warre and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention amongſt our ſelves, how welcome would a Peace and Pacification be to us? what would we give for it if it might be bought? we knew not the ſweetneſſe of Peace before, but our fulneſſe thereof had produced in us a very loathing of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-combe; ſo that ſoule which hath alwayes lived in peace by meanes of the ſtrong man, Luke 11.21. doth ſlight this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113188:9"/>by Chriſt; but when that devils peace is broken, and a poor ſoule is at civill warre in and with it ſelfe, and with ſinne, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan his inſtruments, yea, and with God alſo (who ſeems to take part againſt it, and to wraſtle with it too) O how ſweet is this Peace and Reconciliation with God by Chriſt! there's no ſoule can conceive the ſweetneſſe of it (much leſſe any tongue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it) but that ſoule which hath taſted thereof by ſaving grace, and for love of this (as I may ſo ſay) the ſoule doth prize Chriſt the more.</p>
                  <p>Another benefit is Life; <hi>for Chriſt is the very life of ſuch a ſoul</hi> Col. 3.3, 4. <hi>for by him the ſoule that was dead in ſinnes and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes is quickned,</hi> Eph. 2.1. <hi>he hath breathed his Spirit thereinto and made it a living ſoule,</hi> Rom. 8.10. The man that lyes rotting in his ſinnes is altogether ignorant of the excellency of this new life by Chriſt; as a dead man in the grave is not ſenſible of the ſweetneſſe of bodily life, the living man is he that prizeth life as the beſt Jewell on earth, and will give skin for skin and all that he hath for life; ſo only that ſoule which is raiſed up from the dead to newneſſe of life, feels and findes the excellency and ſweetneſſe thereof, and therefore he alone prizeth Chriſt above all in a reſpect hereof.</p>
                  <p>A third benefit is that Al-healing vertue that this ſoule finds in Chriſt; he is at no time ſick of any malady, but Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, he finds, gives him preſent eaſe; be he never ſo much wearied by labouring under any ſpirituall or temporall burden, any terror, of ſpirit; a broken ſpirit, a ſick body, a ſinking eſtate, a priſion, any tempeſt of tribulation come, he finds Chriſt a ready Haven of reſt, where rides at the Anchor of Hope with ſuch comfort, as he hath a pretty heaven on earth; what would not a man give for ſuch (a Panacea) a Sovereigne receipt (if ſuch one could be found) as would cure all wounds, ſores, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, diſtempers, and lameneſſes in the body? The man that ſhould have ſuch a Medicine would think himſelfe well provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, he would not part with it at any rates; and the ſoule that finds this al-curing vertue in Chriſt, thinks no price ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for him; you cannot offer enough to him for his Chriſt, for indeed he will not leave his Chriſt on any tearmes.</p>
                  <p>A fourth beneſit by Chriſt is, the ſoule by having Chriſt hath
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113188:10"/>himſelfe, and is come to his right wits againe: <hi>Adam</hi> ſeeking by unlawfull meanes to get more knowledge then he had, like men that over-ſtudy themſelves, crackt his braines, and loſt that knowledge which he had before; and his Poſterity to this day, are, yea will be to the laſt day, a company of dictracted perſons, fooliſh and mad children, till Chriſt take them in hand, and by giving them himſelf, bring them againe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: This is evident by that in <hi>Titus</hi> 3.3. where the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeakes of himſelfe and ſuch like, <hi>We our ſelves were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) that is, <hi>out of our minds,</hi> that is, before we had Chriſt we were by-witted perſons; it is worth our obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in this particular, to take notice of what is ſaid concerning the Prodigall at his returne, (which ſignifies the converſion of any ſinner) in <hi>Luke</hi> 15.17. The words are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is, comming, or when he came into himſelfe, he ſaid, &amp;c. Which plainly implyes, the man was before time quite out of himſelfe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.4.</note> and that he both ſaid and did all as a mad man; and ſo madly doe all men carry themſelves before they have Chriſt: And this aggravates their miſery, that they are not ſenſible of this their pittifull condition, neither will be perſwaded to believe it, but like as mad men, think others more mad then themſelves; ſo doe men out of Chriſt think them that are in Chriſt to be mad, their wayes, words and behaviours are ſo ſtrange and uncouth to them:
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.4.</note> But ſuch as are in Chriſt know them that are out of Chriſt to be mad indeed, and they know it by their owne experience, for they themſelves were ſuch at that time; but now they are come to themſelves by Chriſt's comming to them, and for this great bleſſing they prize Chriſt above all.</p>
                  <p>But fifthly, the ſoule that hath ſaving grace, finds by Chriſt it hath not onely received it ſelfe, but it ſelfe with advantage; for by Chriſt he finds an excellency put on himſelfe and all his performances.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. As the touch of the Philoſophers ſtone is ſaid to turne the thing touched into pure gold; ſo more truly, one touch-of Chriſt to a poore ſoule doth metamorphoſe it, making it of great worth, which was before deſpiſed, as vile, and baſe; now he becomes a man of ſome account indeed, both with God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113188:10"/>and good men: He is one of Gods Jewels, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. one of his choſen Generation, one of his holy Nation and peculiar people, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. one that is both precious and honourable in Gods ſight, <hi>Iſa,</hi> 43.4. and therefore one of his beloved ones; briefly, the ſoule that was the pooreſt amongſt Beggars, is by Chriſt made one of the richeſt Kings, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.6.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And beſides this dignity to his perſon, Chriſt alſo digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies all their performances of duty, making them acceptable to God, for all the filth that cleaves to their ſacrifices &amp; holy things he waſheth off, by rincing them in his blood; all their prayers and other preſents offered to God by them, Chriſt perfumes with the odours of his Merits, and ſo repreſents them as ſweet Incenſe to his Father, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.34. That ſoul which hath put on Chriſt, finds him a Garment not onely to cover his nakedneſſe, but alſo to beautifie and adorne him; and this makes the ſoule alſo to prize Chriſt above all, as a man is more choyce of his beſt Apparrell.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, the ſoule that hath ſaving grace finds this admirable commodity alſo by Chriſt, that he gaines by all his loſſes; he ſees all other men loſe by their very gaines; <hi>Paul</hi> in our Text affirmes it in his owne particular caſe, he found now that he loſt by all his ſuppoſed gaines, and that he now did gaine by his ſuppoſed loſſes: Take a ſoule that hath Chriſt, and he will ſay with <hi>David, It was good for me that I was afflicted,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal: 119 71.</note> I got well by it; a priſon will be as gainfull to ſuch a ſoule as it was to <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> who thrived more in the priſon at <hi>Babylon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Chron. 33.11, 12, 13.</note> then in his Pallace at <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> for in his adverſity, he ſought and found his God he loſt in his proſperity; ſuch a ſoule will with the three children, dance in a fiery furnace,
<note place="margin">Dan. 3.25.</note> it will doe him ſo much good, all loſſes and croſſes whatſoever, outward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſpirituall and bodily, bring him in gaine and enrich him, for all things work to his good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. and this not onely all his life long, but alſo at death, when other men loſe moſt, then he gaines moſt; when men out of Chriſt dye and goe hence, they doe not onely leave their goods (as they call them) behind them, but alſo all that little goodneſſe was in them, and ſo goe to that place where is nothing but ſinne and its puniſhment, miſery; a great loſſe indeed they ſuffer, when
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113188:11"/>their fraile Barke of the fleſh ſhipwracks on the mercileſſe Rock of death; but ſuch as have Chriſt, ſaving grace informes them (and they beleeve it as Gods truth) that they ſhall loſe nothing then but what is worſe then nothing,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> their ſinnes and ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which they would faine have parted with before, but could not, it hung ſo faſt to the fleſh; but for that little goodneſſe which was in them, that ſhall be encreaſed and perfected, yea and their goods, they ſhall not loſe, but exchange for better; for Parents, he ſhall have God his heavenly Father, for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and ſiſters, Jeſus Chriſt his eldeſt brother, and the bleſſed Saints; for friends, the holy Angels; for faiding wealth, the true riches; for momentany pleaſures, the everlaſting; for vain titles of honour, immortall glory; yea, for ſorrow joy, for labour reſt, for mortality immortality, and in one word, for his hell here, his Heaven for ever: Is not this a happy change? yet this Chriſt brings to the ſoul, &amp; thetfore you ſee good reaſon it hath to prize him above all; and thus you have the firſt part of the truth made good to you: there is as much reaſon for</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <p>The ſecond part thereof; why ſaving grace makes the ſoule prize Chriſt above all in Juſtification and Sanctification.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> For Juſtification, becauſe ſaving grace doth enlighten the ſoule to ſee the perfection of the Law, which requires an exact performance according to its Rule, in every the leaſt particular, and that for want thereof, it pronounceth a curſe on it, as guilty of the breach of all, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Iames</hi> 2.10. And</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the ſoule by ſaving grace being quickned with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life, is ſenſible of its owne weakneſſe and imperfection, whereby it is diſ-inabled to anſwer the law to its perfect com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, ever in its beſt performances; he finds he cannot doe what he would, much leſſe what he ſhould; and yet doth much what he both would not and ſhould not: Hence it is, that in matter of Juſtification, to obtaine pardon he renounceth all his owne righteouſneſſe as dung and filthy rags, and would not be found in the ſame, but in Chriſt Jeſus the righteous, whoſe righteouſneſſe which is by faith ours, to our ſelves, he ſees muſt (as it only can) free him from guilt of ſinne before Gods Juſtice, and therefore he prizeth Chriſt ſo much above all herein: But this particular hath been ſo clearly manifeſted of late by others, as I ſhall not need further to inſiſt thereon; come we therfore to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113188:11"/>the Reaſons, why ſaving Grace makes the heart prize Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all in ſanctification. They are ſeaven:</p>
                  <p>The firſt is, becauſe ſaving grace diſcovers to the ſoul not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the guilt of ſinne, but alſo the filth of ſinne; and as juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion takes away the guilt, ſo ſanctification doth away the filth of ſinne. And as for the taking away of the guilt, the ſoule de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies it ſelfe and its owne right; ſo for the doing away of the filth the ſoule abhorres it ſelfe in duſt and aſhes, as <hi>Job</hi> 42.6. So that ſaving grace works not onely ſelf-deniall, but alſo a ſelf-loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as in <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7.24. he is even ſicke of himſelfe; the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of ſin that cleaves to him, makes him out of love with himſelfe, and not to endure himſelf with patience, and to ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten him both to God and himſelfe he prizeth Chriſt above all; he finds now his owne garments ſo ſpotted with the fleſh, as he would fain change them, and none in his account like to Chriſts white robes of holineſſe and righteouſneſſe; when a ſoule is ſick of ſinne (as all ſoules are when endued with ſaving grace) a bare pardon will not ſerve their turne, that alone doth not cure them; the Lord muſt heale their tranſgreſſions alſo; now this is by ſanctification, as the former is by juſtification.</p>
                  <p>Another reaſon is, becauſe ſaving grace works the heart to a deſire and longing after the image of God, that it may become like God, as our Saviour often cals us to be. Such a ſoule knows by <hi>Adams</hi> example, that it ſhall not get into a ſtate of innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, till it obtaine the image of God ſtampt on it: Now this i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God conſiſted in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24. and both theſe are by the new man Chriſt Jeſus, in whom we are created to the good works of them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. for he is the image of the Father, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.15. and therefore that the ſoule may be holy as his heavenly Father, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.16. and righteous as he is righteous, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. laſt. he prizeth Chriſt above all, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the treaſury of all grace, from whom he muſt receive grace for grace, <hi>John</hi> 1.16.</p>
                  <p>A third Reaſon is, from the diſcovery of heaven to the ſoule that hath ſaving grace: for hereby, as through a perſpective Glaſſe, he can looke into heaven, and there he findes nothing but happineſſe and holineſſe, as in hell there is nothing but ſin and miſery. As no good can goe to hell, ſo he ſees no bad, no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113188:12"/>ſinfull and uncleane thing can get entrance into heaven, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.27. ſaving grace tels him (and he beleeves it) that without ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe he ſhall not ſee Gods face in heaven, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he followes it with ſuch earneſtneſſe of deſire and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and prizeth Chriſt, in whom all holineſſe is ſtored up for us, above all things whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, ſaving grace taketh a mans heart off from his own ends in all things, and teacheth him to ſeek Chriſt, not ſo much for ſelfe-ends, as Chriſts ends. When the Lord doth convert a ſoule to him, and workes ſaving grace in his heart; as he gives him a new principle to worke by, ſo he gives him new ends to worke for. Before converſion Selfe is all in all to a man; Selfe ſets him at worke, and he workes altogether by ſelfe principles and to ſelfe ends; God is not in all his thoughts, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 10.4. for indeed ſelfe is his God. But when God comes to take his place againe in the heart, and to be God to a ſoule, then he becomes the utmoſt end of that ſoule alſo; ſo that as he will do nothing but by him, commanding and ſtrengthning, ſo he does all to him and for him; the ſoule is now lifted up above it ſelfe, it ſoares aloft at greater matters then belong to ſelfe: Selfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matters are but as flies in his Eagle eye; he ſtoops not to them, but as the ponderous fleſh makes him; his alme is altogether at the glory of God, magnifying Chriſt, forwarding the Kingdome of the Lord Jeſus, building up his Church, and repairing the breaches thereof, &amp;c. Like as good and true Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men looke not ſo much at their owne profits as the common good, ſo the true Chriſtian aimes at the publike good of Chriſt, the advancing of his Kingdome here, more then at their owne advancement by him: He doth not deſire Chriſt ſo much to be ſaved by him, as that Chriſt may be ſerved by him. The ſoul that prizeth Chriſt above al only for juſtification, ſeeks him for ſelfe ends, that is, for happineſſe and ſalvation by him; and thus a ſoule doth before he hath ſaving grace: But to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him above all for ſanctification, is to prize and deſire Chriſt for Chriſt's owne ends, that we may be made holy by him, and ſo become zealous of good workes, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.14. and that we may ſerve him all the dayes of our life in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.7 4, 75. And thus to deſire Chriſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113188:12"/>for Chriſt, ſaving grace teacheth the ſoule, and to doe all for him; becauſe ſuch a ſoule makes Chriſt its Maſter, and ſelf muſt be his ſervant, ſo that ſelfe muſt now wait till his Maſter is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: Selfe may attend at the doore of the heart, but Chriſt as Maſter beares all the ſway there, and as he will, ſo the heart ſaith he ſhall be ſerved whoſoever goes unſerved; and as for ſelfe, ſuch a ſoule as is principled with ſaving grace, looks at ſelfe as beſt ſerved when his Maſter is moſt ſerved: There is a ſweet and holy emulation betweet ſuch a ſoule and Chriſt; that as Chriſt takes all that is done to that ſoule as done to himſelfe ſo that ſoule takes all done to Chriſt as done to himſelfe; and therfore is of opinion that he ſerves himſelf beſt when he ſerves Chriſt moſt: Yea, he leaves ſelfe to Chriſt's diſpoſall and good will, knowing that he is a good, loving and free maſter indeed, that will ſuffer his ſervant to want no good thing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, ſaving grace frames the heart to a conjugall affection of Chriſt, to ſuch a love of him as is between husband and wife, ſo that the ſoule loves the perſon of Chriſt as well as his porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea and deſires him more for his perſons ſake, then for his portions ſake; all the note of ſuch a ſoule is that with the Spouſe in <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16. <hi>My beloved is mine, and I am his;</hi> this heart is enamoured with Chriſt, becauſe of that exceeding beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of holineſſe in him; he is to her the faireſt of ten thouſand: This ſoule loves not Chriſt ſo much for that which comes by him, as for that ſhee ſees in him; when God married us (as he ſaith he hath married us, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14.) his free grace had reſpect on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to our perſons, and not for any portion of ours, whereby he might be enriched and benefited: Hence we find a love of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind (for ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſignifies) aſcribed to him, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.4.
<note place="margin">Job 14.15.</note> which <hi>Job's</hi> words doe well interpret to us, ſaying, <hi>Thou (O Lord) haſt a deſire to the worke of thine hands:</hi> Wherein is hinted the reaſon of Gods affection to us, not any worth in us, but his right to us; it is his free grace which makes him owne that his right, and the ſame free grace in the heart of a man reflects on God the ſame work; that ſoule affects more Chriſt's perſon then any or all the things that come by him: It is but a kind of whoriſh ſpirit to love him onely for what he hath, and to get by him; that Spouſe that loves her Husband's perſon as ſhee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113188:13"/>ought, will love him when he is poore as well as rich, when ſick as well, will cleave to him in his neceſſity, content to live in priſon with him, to goe a begging and be baniſhed with him: ſo where ſaving grace is, the heart loves Chriſts perſon ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potently, as ſhee will cleave to him in all his neceſſities; when naked and poore, ſhee will love him as well as when rich and bravely attired with outward pompe; if he goe to priſon ſhee will goe too, rather then part with her beſt beloved ſhee will go a begging with him, into baniſhment with him, into the midſt of fire any faggot, yea into hell too rather then leave him; for ſhee knowes hell would be no hell to her if he be with her, and that a heaven would be a hell if he be not in it, or ſhee find him not therein.</p>
                  <p>A ſixth Reaſon why ſuch a heart as hath ſaving grace doth prize Chriſt above all in matter of Sanctification, is, becauſe it knowes and feeles as great a want of Gods free grace therein as in matter of Juſtification: For we are as unable to ſanctifie our ſelves as to juſtifie our ſelves; yea we can doe more to procure ſanctification to our ſelves then to obtaine juſtification; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as we find the good work of ſanctification in us aſcribed to the Lord, both for the beginning and perfecting of it in <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.6. ſo we find it attributed to his good pleaſure, that is, his free grace, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. and indeed if we doe ſeriouſly weigh things, Gods free grace ſeems to abound more in the ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſoule, then in his juſtification of it; for by juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he doth onely acquit it of the guilt of ſinne committed, but by ſanctification he doth not onely purge it from the filth of ſinne committed, (wich equallizeth the guilt) but alſo ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the ſoule againſt ſinne not committed; Sanctification d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th not onely heale ſinne in us, but preſerves us from the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction thereof, and it is a greater mercy to be preſerved from a miſery, then to be delivered out of it; wherefore ſuch as pin Gods free grace onely to our juſtification, ſeem to me, without warrant from the Word, too much to ſtraight-lace the full Breaſts of Gods free grace, from whence a poor ſoule may ſuch as much comfort for its ſanctification as for its juſtification, and that in regard of his daily failings, which ſhew him his wants thereof, and drive him to the Throne of Grace for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113188:13"/>ſupply; now Chriſt is the Store-houſe of Gods free grace, what meaſure ſoever we have of it, it is conveyed to us in and through him, not onely that free grace of Juſtification, but alſo our Sanctification; he is made both to us one as well as the other, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. and as he willingly laid downe his life for to juſtifie us, ſo he did as willingly ſanctifie himſelf that we might be ſanctified by him in truth, <hi>John</hi> 17.19. which doth plainly intimate that a ſoule can no more be ſanctified without Chriſt, then it can be juſtified without him; and this the ſoule that hath ſaving grace, doth know very well, and therefore prizeth Chriſt above all in ſanctification as well as in juſtification.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, ſaving grace puts the ſoule wherein it is, upon get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an aſſurance of its Juſtification; ſuch a ſoule will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve every report of the deceitfull heart, but will examine the truth of it: Before ſaving grace comes, all that the heart ſaith, is taken to be as true as the Goſpell, and thence it is that men before converſion dreame of Heaven and happineſſe; and hell, they are quite out of any feare of it: it is otherwiſe after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and therefore the converted ſoule will ſtill be ſearching its evidence for Heaven, and his chiefeſt work is to make: that ſure to him: This is eaſily collected from the Apoſtles Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations hereto, <hi>Worke out your ſalvation</hi> (ſaith he) that is,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.12. 2 Pet. 1.10.</note> the aſſurance of it to your ſelves; <hi>and give al diligence think no pains too much to make your calling and election ſure;</hi> not in themſelves for that they are already, but ſure to you, which as yet they are not, or at leaſt not ſo fully as they may and ought to be; But no aſſurance can we have of our Juſtification but by our Sanctification; truly they that perſwade men to goe firſt to Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificrtion to get aſſurance of God's free grace to them, doe ſet them to unwind that fathomeleſſe bottome at the wrong end, and ſo makes the poore ſoules to coſter matters together as they cannot cleere their aſſurance to themſelves: You know that when you would unwind a bottome of threed, you muſt begin at the laſt end that is outmoſt, next to you, and viſible to your ſight; and by following that, you ſhall come to the firſt end, which at the firſt lay hid from your eyes, &amp; you could not come at; thus muſt you deale with a bottome of God's free grace, in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113188:14"/>working out the aſſurance of your ſalvation to your own ſouls; and to make it more perſpicuous to your underſtandings, I ſhall briefly unfold the whole myſtery thereof: Free grace in the worke of ſalvation runs in three channels, the ſeverall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof (which are many) are reduceable to theſe three heads. Firſt, The ſeparation of Gods people from the wicked. Secondly, the freeing of them from ſinne. And thirdly, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feofeing them to the inheritance: each of theſe are carried about with many ſucceſſive acts of free grace, but the firſt &amp; the laſt are in each particular moſt remarkable: In the ſeparation of them from the wicked, the firſt link of the chain is Election, the laſt is Vocation; in the freeing of them from ſinne: The firſt is Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, the laſt is Sanctification; and concerning the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the firſt is Adoption, and the laſt is Glorification: Now of theſe ſix, three are in God, and three in us; the firſt three are in God from all eternity, the laſt three are wrought in us, in time after we have a being, and it is worth your diligence to obſerve how the firſt and laſt three doe ſweetly anſwer to each other; for as by election we are ſeparated in Gods purpoſe from the wretched Maſſe of the Reprobates, ſo by effectuall vocation we are ſeparated actually from the prophane Maſſe of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full world: And as by Juſtification we are freed from the guilt and condemnation of ſinne, ſo by Sanctification from the fact and pollution of it; and as by Adoption we are made heirs and ſonnes, ſo by Glorification (begun here and perfected hereafter) we are put into actuall poſſeſſion of our glorious Inheritance: Thus have you a Breviate of that great work of our ſalvation, and by it you may eaſily perceive where you muſt begin in the work of aſſuring any of the three generall heads; as would you aſſure your ſelfe of the firſt generall, whoſe firſt and laſt ends were Election and Vocation; would you begin at Election? No, that end which is firſt to God-ward muſt be laſt to us, as that which is firſt to us is laſt to God in working; where God ends there we muſt begin, and that is in this particular at our Vocation; and this the Apoſtle plainly intimates in ſaying, <hi>Make your calling and election ſure,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.10. Why puts he calling before election? why did he not ſay election and calling, ſince election is farre long before calling? The reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113188:14"/>though election is firſt in being, yet it is laſt in exiſting and appearing to be to us: Our Vocation appeares firſt to us, though in order of being it is indeed laſt; and therefore in ſeeking out our election, the Apoſtle implies we ſhould begin at our Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo from what we beſt know to proceed to that we leaſt know: So for the ſecond Generall, the freedome from ſin, whoſe firſt and laſt links are Juſtification and Sanctification; ſhall we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at Juſtification? No, that end is the firſt end which is hid in God from our eyes, till we have unreaved the bottome; we muſt begin at that end which is next us, which is outmoſt and viſible to us, and that is Sanctification; God's free grace to us is aſſured on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his free grace in us: We cannot be aſſured of the freedome from the guilt of ſinne, till we be find a freedome from the fact, filthineſſe and power of ſinne; and the reaſon is, becauſe whom he juſtifies he ſanctifies, and both by one and the ſame meanes, not at one and the ſame time; for he juſtifies us to God from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and therefore is called <hi>the Lambe that was ſlaine from</hi> (that is,
<note place="margin">Revel. 13.8.</note> before) <hi>the beginning of the World;</hi> but we are ſanctified by him in time after we have a being; but the meanes which he imployes in both our Juſtification and Sanctification are the ſame; for as we juſtified by his Active and Paſſive Obedience, by his death and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, by his reſurrection, &amp;c. ſo we are ſanctified by them; for the vertue of them (as <hi>Paul</hi> in our Text cals it) doth work in us, to the killing of ſinne in us, and quickning of us to new Obedience:
<note place="margin">As Chriſt died for our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſo for our Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Titus 2.14. Luke 1.75.</note> as they take away the guilt of ſinne, ſo they free us from the filth and dominion of ſinne; ſo that you muſt know this for a truth, that you cannot be aſſured of Chriſt's living to you in your Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, untill you can find him living in you by Sanctification: Our Apoſtle knew ſo much, and therefore when he would have the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to get aſſurance of their ſalvation by Chriſt, he ſends them home into themſelves, ſaying, <hi>prove your ſelves,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.5.</note> 
                     <hi>examine your ſelves whether you be in the Faith,</hi> that is, in the eſtate of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which we call Salvatione And how ſhall they know this? He tels them by adding, for know you not that except Chriſt be in you, you are Reprobates, that is, ſuch as are excluded from that happineſſe: Now by Chriſt being in us is meant our Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as (to ſpeak ſtrictly) our being in Chriſt looks at, and chiefly implies our Juſtification; though indeed this phraſe in Chriſt is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113188:15"/>uſed ſometimes in a large ſenſe for both, but to draw this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to a cloſe, the Apoſtle ſends the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to their ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a proofe juſtification; and till they can find Chriſt in them by his ſanctifying them, they cannot conclude any thing but that for all they know as yet they are Reprobates; and hence it is that a good ſoule earneſtly lahouring for aſſurance (which is the very ſoule and life of a Chriſtians comfort here) doth ſo highly prize Chriſt for ſanctification; and thus you have the truth confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in both parts: come we now to Application.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                  </label> The Uſe that at this time I ſhall deſire you with me to make of that truth we have heard, is to goe to a tryall of our ſelves, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we have ſaving grace or no: Truly (my Beloved) ſelf-exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is a duty of great conſequence, and neceſſary to the wel-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yea to the very being of a Chriſtian indeed; it is the very key of the work of aſſurance: Hence the Apoſtle when he ſets them about the work of aſſurance, firſt directs them to take examination of themſelves in hand. Let us not then truſt to the reports of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull hearts who will be ready enough to ſooth us up with a vain and fruitleſſe hrpe of God's free grace in Chriſt: Alas, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are gone to hell with this hope that Chriſt dyed for them! their ſalfe hearts told them they ſhould be ſaved, and they beleeving them ſate down in ſecurity and ſought no further till it was too late, ſo late as Heaven gate was ſhut againſt them, as the fooliſh Virgins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.10, 11. But this is a truth, that if we be in the ſtate of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (and ſo may aſſure our ſelves we ſhall be ſaved for ever) then there is ſaving grace in us; and if we have ſaving grace in us, we prize Chriſt above all things both for Juſtification and Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo then the point whereof we are to examine our ſelves, is our prizing of Chriſt above all in the particulars before mentioned; and for the cleerer diſcovery of the truth therein, we will draw up the rules of our examination into two ranks, anſwerable to the proofe of the poſition delivered: As</p>
               <p>Firſt, whether we prize Chriſt above all.</p>
               <p>Secondly, whether we prize Chriſt above all both in Juſtification and Sanctification. Firſt</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <p>Whether we prize Chriſt above all: If ſaving grace be in us, ſo will we eſteem of Chriſt as more worth then all; we have not time to inſtance in every particular ſaving grace; we ſhall therefore at
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113188:15"/>this time but mention one, which is accounted as a Mother grace, and that is faith. Have we but that ſaving grace, Chriſt will be a Pearle of great price in our eye; and you have a cleare proofe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by the Teſtimony of <hi>Peter,</hi> who ſayth, <hi>To you that beleeve he</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>is precious, but to them that beleeve not he is a ſtone of offence,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.7. <hi>Now to beleeve, is to receive Chriſt,</hi> John 1.12. and by the rule of contraries, not to beleeve is not to receive Cſtriſt; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtles words hold forth to us, that Chriſt is precious onely to ſuch as have received him; and to ſuch as have not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him he is but as a peble ſtone, nay which is worſe, a rock of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, whereon they ſtrike in deſpight, and make an utter ſhipwrack of their ſoules: So then, if we prize Chriſt, we have received him; now the Queſtion will be, whether we have received Chriſt or no; to determine this caſe, we will onely conſider the manner of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving him; for that is ſo remarkable as it will reſolve this doubt if we can find it to have beene in us.</p>
                  <p>If you ask, what is the true manner of receiving Chriſt? I anſwer, that the ſoule which receives Chriſt truly and ſavingly, takes him with a holy kind of greedineſſe; we receive him with ſo much ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe of affection, as they which took Heaven by violence, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.12. as if we took Chriſt by force out of the armes of his Father even when he freely holds him out to us; a kind of behaviour diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to men, but herein moſt acceptable to God: We are like hunger-ſtarven men, whoſe hot appetite doth make them ſo earneſt after victuals, as when offered by a charitable hand, they doe take them with ſuch earneſtneſſe, as they ſeeme rather violently to ſnatch then civilly to receive them; ſuch a diſpoſition God loves to ſee in us, and therefore hath called ſuch perſons bleſſed, and prommiſed them a full ſatisfaction, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.6. Yea, he knowes that till we be ſuch, we will not truly receive him, and therefore he cals onely ſuch to take him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. But leaſt you ſhould wonder at this, I will briefly ſhew you how it comes to paſſe: The Lord poures the healing Oyle of ſaving grace into none but broken Veſſels, he brings down ſuch as he intends to exalt, and before he beſtowes his Chriſt on any ſoule, he will make that ſoul know and feel his want of Chriſt: And why? becauſe the ſight of his want of Chriſt will make him prize Chriſt, ſeeke Chriſt, and to praiſe his free grace for Chriſt given to him. Now to make a ſoule ſee his want of Chriſt, he ſets
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113188:16"/>all his ſinnes in order before him,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.21.</note> reckons with him to the utmoſt farthing, and ſo ſhewes him how much he is endebted to his juſtice, which cals for execution on him, to bind him here with great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles and fetters of temporall and ſpirituall plagues and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſo to lead him to the infernall priſon of hell. He makes him ſee that he is not able to anſwer one of a thouſand,
<note place="margin">Job 9.3.</note> much leſſe to cleer his ſcores with him; and therefore he muſt get him a Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to diſcharge the debt for him, or elſe he muſt be committed to the Goaler; and he finds no creature worth any thing neere the matter to be able to pay off for him the leaſt farthing of his debt; ſo that the poor ſoul is followed with fears and terrours, as it is even ready to give up all hope; but then the Lord reveales Chriſt to the ſoule and his fulneſſe of riches, whereby he is able to diſcharge all his debts, and make him not onely a free man, but alſo a rich man; that Chriſt hath ſufficient to ſet him out of debt and to ſet him up again, yea &amp; to keep him from being a bankrupt with his God again; and withall the Lord ſeems to whiſper in the eare of the ſoule, that this rich Chriſt may be his; he doth not ſay aloud and openly at the firſt, I will give thee my Chriſt for thy Surety, though he be fully and really minded ſo to doe; but Chriſt is offered more hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly at the firſt, by way of an overture (as we ſay) and this glimpſe of Chriſt ſets the heart on longing for him, and his deſire of Chriſt makes him labour for Chriſt, and the more he ſeeks him, the more he ſees him and the abundancy in him, which ſtill ſharpens his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and quickens his endeavours: The more he feels Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, the more he hales and puls at Chriſt; faine would he now have his fill of this full Chriſt, and when once he layes hold on him by faith, with what greedineſſe ſucks he him in? when a man that is ſo thirſty, as that he thinks his heart will cone for dright, and he ſhall be choakt, doth take the bottle, wich what greedineſſe doth he ſwallow downe, as if he could never have enough? So doth the ſoule take down Chriſt that hunger and thirſts after him; it ſeems inſatiable of Chriſt, and that he can never have enough of Chriſt; and therefore he layes aſide all to get Chriſt. For the purpoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the carriage of the Samaritane woman in <hi>Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 4. Chriſt who went about doing good, with his continuall travaile had wearied his weak fleſh (which was ſubject to the ſame infirmities that ours is excepting ſinne) and therefore he ſate downe on the Well an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113188:16"/>was thirſty, yet he was not ſo weary but he would be doing good, as opportunity was offered; and therefore when the woman came (to whom he meant to give himſelfe) to awaken her and let her ſee her ſinnes, he examines her, yea, and tels her of her Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and of living waters which he had to give, yea, he reveals him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to her, and then ſhee preſently left her water-pots: So when any ſoule receiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Chriſt, all the affections thereof ſeeme to runne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as in one full ſtreame to him; Water-pots, outward and worldly imployments muſt ſtand by a while; the ſoule hath no leizure as yet to mind them: As if all things then were to the ſoul (as indeed they are) nothing in compariſon of Chriſt; profit, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, credit, and ſuch like worldly friends muſt ſtand aſide now, the ſoule hath do leizure to talk with them for giving Chriſt enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment: nothing will goe downe with this ſoule but Chriſt; he takes up all his thoughts and affections, he cannot but think of his Chriſt, all the talk he loves, is of and with his Chriſt. In <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.5. the new married man was freed to ſtay at home the firſt yeere from going forth to warre, or bearing any publike office, that he might rejoyce himſelfe with his wife, knowing that all the Jewiſh ceremonies were types; I have often conſidered what this ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny might ſignifie, and truly I can find nothing that anſwers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to more fitly then the freedome a poore ſoule new married to Chriſt muſt and will have from all worldly imployments for to enjoy her Chriſt, and to ſolace herſelfe with him; and if the indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent fleſh neceſſitate her to earthly affaires, ſhee goes about them as one deep in love, ſcarce minding the worke he is about, his heart is elſwhere, and he cannot follow his work, he muſt goe ſee his Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: And in her abſence will ſit down and think on her, if friends come, he will talk of her to them; was it not juſt ſo with <hi>Paul?</hi> there was no ſooner the match made between Chriſt and him, but he was wholy taken up with Chriſt, he minded nothing but Chriſt, breathed nothing but Chriſt, all his diſcourſe was of Chriſt; How full of Chriſt are all his Epiſtles? How much was he delighted even with the very name of Chriſt Jeſus, that in ſo few leaves he repeats it many hundred times? It was ſugar in his mouth, and he loved the ſweet reliſh it had: Nothing ſo ſweet to him as Chriſt; nay, in compariſon of him, all things elſe were more bitter then wormwood to him; his very beſt and moſt gainfull commodities
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113188:17"/>(which were ſo precious once to him) are now but loſſe and dung too; Chriſt is the onely ſweet and profitable: Thus alſo <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> when ſhee knew Chriſt as her Chriſt, with what aflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on received ſhee him? ſhee loved him exceeding much; ſhee thought nothing too much for him, he ſhall have her box of precious Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſhee waſhes his feet with her teares which ſhee wept for joy of him. The ſoule that hath Chriſt is even overjoyed (as I may ſay) when but come to touch his very feet; ſo ſtrong is her deſires of him: So when the Merchant had found the Pearle of great price, the ſtrength of his affection thereto took him off from all other things, and carried him with an earneſtneſſe thereto: So then the ſoule that prizeth Chriſt, hath received him with ſuch greedineſſe, as to think he can never have enough of him, and therefore he can neither take too much paines, nor be at too much coſt for Chriſt; ſuch a ſoule will run through thick and thin for Chriſt, and leap over all hinderances to get more of him: and this is the firſt ſigne of our prizing of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond mark ſhall be the temper of our ſoules when we have loſt the ſight and ſenſe of Chriſt, after we have received him; for ſo it comes to paſſe very often, that the ſoule ſeems to have loſt his Chriſt; and, to ſay truth, Chriſt hath juſt cauſe many times to hide himſelfe from a ſoule; as when the ſoule begins to ſet looſe from him, which the ſoule is apt to doe after the heat of its firſt love is over; like as hungry and thirſty men ſet light by victuals when their hunger and thirſt is killed and they filled; in ſuch a caſe, Chriſt doth like a tender Parent that finds his child regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of him, leaving him to runne after this and that flower in the field, will hide himſelfe and put his child in a feare that he hath left him to himſelfe, and he muſt ſhift for himſelfe, which he cannot doe: So dealt the Lord with <hi>David</hi> in Pſal. 30.6, 7. The Sunne of God's favour was riſen to a great hight, and ſhined ſo hot on him, as it warmed him to his very heart, ſo that he grew frolicke againe, and dreamt that this his merry world would laſt ever: He thought this Heaven would be alwayes cleere to him without clouds; but his Sunne ſet even at noon-day to him: His frolickneſſe was but againſt a ſtorme which was at hand, for in the next words he addes, <hi>But thou didſt bids thy face:</hi> Againe, we doe often make great clouds which doe eclipſe the Sunne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113188:17"/>to us, that we neither ſee him, nor feele any heat and warmth from him: Theſe clouds are our iniquities, which make a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration between him and us, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.2. Now in this caſe when Chriſt hath given us the ſlip, and on the ſudden hath conveyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from us, let us conſider how our ſoules behave themſelves, and by their behaviour now, we may know whether they prize Chriſt as they ought: <hi>David</hi> tels you he was troubled; think not (Beloved) that he was troubled but a little, for he was fore trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, as the word is tranſlated in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.21. It is a terrible trouble, as the Word indeed fully ſignifies; for then it is with the ſoule, as it is with a man that hath loſt a Jewell wherein all his wealth conſiſted; O how is the poore man troubled! how doth terrour and feare ſeize on him, that he quivers and ſhakes againe? how doth he hunt up and downe and ſeek every corner for it? he turnes all upſide downe, and cannot be quiet till he hath it, for he knowes he is utterly undone if he find it not againe: ſo the ſoule that hath loſt her Chriſt, her Pearle, is exceedingly troubled, and doth not reſt contented with any thing till ſhee hath found him againe, ſhee muſt have Chriſt or elſe ſhee is undone for ever: See this cleared by the example of the Spouſe in <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.4, 5. you may ſee her rejoycing in Chriſt; O how ſweet is he to her! but in the ſixt Verſe you find her at a loſſe; Her wel-beloved hath withdrawn himſelfe and is gone from her; and mark (I pray you) how heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhee takes it; Her heart went with him, ſhee faints, ſhee laments, ſhee ſeeks him, ſhee cals him, ſhee enquires after him, ſhee goes to the Watch-men, the Miniſters of the Goſpell, and to her Siſters, common Chriſtians, to ask after him, ſhee cryes him in the ſtreets, <hi>Did you ſee my beloved O when you ſee him tell him I am ſicke of love;</hi> ſo ſtrong was her love to him, that ſhee was ſicke for him, and ſhee never left ſeeking him till ſhee found him, in chap. 6. ver. 7. where ſhee embraceth him againe. Thus it is with every poore ſoule that hath once had Chriſt, and Union and Communion with him, when he doth hide himſelfe therefrom; all the rattles and tinkling comforts of this world will not quiet him; he muſt have his Chriſt, or elſe he cryes, Undone, Undone: As <hi>Rachel</hi> ſaid, <hi>give me children or elſe I dye;</hi> ſo he cryes, O if you love me give me Chriſt, Chriſt, or elſe I dye, I dye eternally: If he meet not Chriſt in prayer, at a Sermon, at a Sacrament, in an Ordinance,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113188:18"/>how doth he hunt after his Chriſt? He ſeeks not for Chriſts, but for Chriſt himſelfe, and therefore he could be content to goe a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for Chriſt, if Chriſt were in the fiery furnace, yea in hell, this ſoule that hath once had him, will be content to goe thither for him; ſo much is he troubled for Chriſt, as he thinks himſelfe in hell already without him: Let us now (Beloved) look home, and ſee whether we have at any time been thus troubled for our Chriſt; alas, have we not been much more troubled and terrified with the loſſe of a kind Husband, a loving Wife, a good child, a neere and deere friend, then for the loſſe of Chriſt? Have we not been more troubled at outward croſſes, when the world hath frowned on us, then when our Chriſt hath turned away his face from us? Have we not been more inquiſitive after our Gold and Silver, and tooke more paines to regaine the ſame, then ever we did for a loſt Chriſt? Thus if it have been with us, then Chriſt is not precious in our eyes; for to ſuch a ſoule as prizeth Chriſt truly, the loſſe of Chriſt is more to him, then the loſſe of all Husbands, wives, children, friends, gold, ſilver, and what elſe is in the world of any worth and value in the eyes of men; and ſo you have a ſecond marke to try your ſelves by.</p>
                  <p>A third Token of our prizing Chriſt above all, is taken from the affection of ſuch a ſoule to Chriſt, after ſhee hath loſt him and ſought him, but he will not be found; for this you muſt know (Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) that when Chriſt is gone, he will ſtay his owne time; like as the Father which hath hid himſelfe from his child, will ſtay ſo long as he ſees good, though his child cry never ſo loud, and call Father father never ſo often; ſo Chriſt when he hath withdrawne himſelfe, will ſtay ſo long as he pleaſeth, though the poor ſoule cry for him and to him never ſo much: Now in this ſad condition when Chriſt ſeems not to love the poor ſoul in any the leſt meaſure, when he will not accept of any of her love tokens, but flings back prayers and performances, and will none of them; that ſoule which prizeth Chriſt above all, loves Chriſt ſtill for all this; though Chriſt ſeem to forſake her, yet ſhee will not forſake Chriſt; ſhee will not let her hold goe of him; ſhee will owne Chriſt, though Chriſt will not owne her; ſhee will tell Chriſt, I will love thee Chriſt, though thou wilt not love me; I ſee worth in thee that thou ſhouldeſt be beloved, though thou ſeeſt no worth in me; <hi>thou
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113188:18"/>art the faireſt of ten thouſand,</hi> the moſt beautiful that ever I laid mine eye on, I cannot but love thee, though I am ſo black and deformed in thy ſight, as thou wilt not love me; thou art a good Husband, and bleſſed is that ſoule that getteth thee for her Husband: Ah my Chriſt, make me but as one of thy hired ſervants, if thou wilt not make me thy Spouſe, or one of thy children: Such a ſoule will ſay to Chriſt, tell me my Chriſt why thou haſt thus with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne thy ſelfe from me, let me know mine offence which I have committed againſt thee, and made thee thus to leave me; and if thou wilt have me I will goe to Hell to avenge my ſelfe on my ſelfe on my ſelfe for it: I take it as a great favour that thou ſuffereſt me to board with thy children, though thou wilt not owne me as one of thine; it glads my heart to ſee the feaſt of fat things, the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of thy Ordinances which thou provideſt for thy people, though I taſte not the ſweetneſſe of them, I will not raile on thee in Hell, for thou art a good Chriſt, and I ſhall thank none but my fooliſh ſelfe for my loſſe of thee; thus will the ſoule that prizeth Chriſt above all hold faſt by Chriſt ſtill, and claſp him in her affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, though he ſeeme to neglect her altogether; this you may ſee evidently in <hi>David</hi> in ſuch a condition; mark his words in Pſal. 22.1, 2. <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me, and art ſo far from helping me, and from the words of my roaring? O my God I cry in the day time but thou heareſt not, and in the night ſeaſon I am not ſilent:</hi> wherein you have <hi>David</hi> to his owne ſenſe in a loſt condition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had loſt his God: and three things are obſervable in his words: Firſt, the great anguiſh and griefe of his heart, which appeares by the loudneſſe of his complaint, and the continuance thereof; He roares, he cries day and night for his God. Secondly, and yet God ſeems to him to ſtop both his eares, he will not heare him, he makes him no anſwer, but lets him goe on roaring and crying for and after him: And for all this in the third place mark how the good ſoule cleaves faſt to God; he will have God to be his God ſtill, though God ſeems to reject him out of the number of his people; and this is apparent by his calling God his God, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>My God,</hi> and that not once, but againe and againe, my God. Truly they are the words of a ſaving faith that prizeth the Lord above all, and therefore will by no tentation be beaten off from him; but where this high eſteeme of him is not, there you ſhall
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113188:19"/>find the quite contrary; as between two men that have no great eſtimation of each other, if one ſlight the other, he ſhall be ſlighted as much againe; ſo when the ſoule prizeth not Chriſt, if he caſt it off, that is, bring it into judgement, croſſes and loſſes, that ſoul will caſt off Chriſt and his ſervice: All frownes drive this ſoule off from Chriſt; for this ſoul loves Chriſts more then Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and when Chriſt wil let her have no more of his Love-tokens he ſhall have no more of her love; then as they ſaid of <hi>David, who is the ſonne of Jeſſe?</hi> ſo they of Chriſt, <hi>who is this Jeſus? is he not the Carpenters ſonne?</hi> and with that wicked King, <hi>This evill commeth of the Lord, why ſhould I wait for the Lord any longer?</hi> 2 Kin. 6.33. This ſprings from that bitter root of undervaluing the Lord and overvaluing our ſelves; but where there is a true eſteeme of God, there is this waiting and ſeeking ſpirit, as in <hi>Micah</hi> 7.7. the Church of God ſayth, <hi>I will looke unto the Lord, I will wait for the God of my ſalvation, my God</hi> (mark that) <hi>will heare me:</hi> Beloved, let us aske our ſelves this queſtion, in theſe dark times wherein our Sunne ſeems to be ſetting, for the wild beaſts of all ſorts, that prey on God's ſervants and his truth, come apace out of their Dens, and we have faſted and prayed many times, many and great cryes have we made to our God for his returne, and yet he anſwers not; how is it now with our hearts? how ſtand they affected towards God? doth his abſence coole our affection to him? doth his delay of anſwer diſhearten us from calling to him? doe we ſet looſe from him, becauſe we ſee him ſetting looſe from us? then we never loved nor prized him as we ought: But if his going from us make us runne after him, if the ſenſe of his loſſe quicken our love to him, and the leſſe he ſeems to heare the louder we cry, and never give over night nor day, then we doe prize him above all; and ſo you have the third rule of tryall.</p>
                  <p>A fourth may be this; the ſoule that prizeth Chriſt ſets him uppermoſt, as in his thoughts ſo in his actions, he is the top-end of them all: He doth all for Chriſt; as all Rivers run unto the Ocean from whence they firſt came, ſo all the actions of a Chriſt-prizing ſoule run wholy to Chriſt as they came from him; all this ſoules note is, Chriſt muſt be obeyed, Chriſt muſt be pleaſed, Chriſt muſt be honoured; Jewels, Plate, and ſuch like precious things are ſet in ſome eminent &amp; peſpicuous place, that they may be ſeen;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113188:19"/>ſo he that prizeth Chriſt, holds him forth in his words and deeds to be ſeen of all men; in a word, this ſoule takes Chriſt for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ſo that Chriſt is firſt and laſt to him; firſt, as his Commander, and laſt as his End; he doth all by his word and to his glory; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he knowes Chriſt is the beſt Maſter; there is never ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: He is the wiſeſt, moſt able to direct; the ſtrongeſt, moſt able to protect, and the freeſt of all to his ſervants; if they ask any thing of him, which is for their good, he denies them not; he gives the beſt wages and the faireſt livery too, for it is even the ſame cloth that himſelfe weares of, ſo that God his Father ſees but little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt Maſter and Servant.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obect. </seg>
                     </label> But happily ſome poore ſoule will ſay, alas, wooe's me, I thought I had prized Chriſt aright, but now I ſee I doe not, for I find other things mixt with Chriſt, Chriſt is not my only mover.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> A weak ſoule will ſtumble, and may fall at a little ſtone in its way, ſuch as this is, and therefore I muſt take it up and remove it; and ſo to doe, I muſt entreat the poore ſoule that hath ſtumbled at this ſigne, to conſider what is the firſt Wheele that moves in his actions; let him find out the <hi>(primum mobile)</hi> firſt mover, for he it is that gives the denomination to this act, though many other things fall in with it by the way: If love of Chriſt be the firſt Wheele that moves, then though other wheeles may move toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him, yet he is thy Maſter, thy head and Jewell; like as a jurney to London is ſo called, becauſe a deſire to ſee that famous City, and an intent to goe thereunto, moved firſt to the ſetting forth thereon, though by the way a man doe many other buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; ſo our actions may be truly ſaid to be for Chriſt, if our love of, and obedience to him firſt moved us thereunto, though by the way we ſee and meet with many conveniences to our ſelves. My Beloved, the doing of duty is compared to ſowing of Corne, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.6. and <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.8. The ſower ſoweth the pureſt ſeed he can, to have pure Corne againe, and yet the pureſt will have husks if not other ſoyle; ſo when a ſoule doth duty, he would doe it as purely, as cleanly as he can, and yet thou findeſt ſome husks clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thereto, a husk of pride, oſtentation, ſelf-ſeeking, &amp;c. In this caſe you muſt ſift your heart over, till you find out the firſt mover, thy firſt intent and purpoſe in the ſame, and if Chriſt were that, then is he thy Maſter; but if he were not firſt, but the ſecond, then
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113188:20"/>he is none of thy Maſter: Divide the ends of thy action, and then ſee if thou wouldſt have done it, if there had beene none but Cſtriſt as thy end; many men in theſe dayes have done much in ſhew for Chriſt and his Cauſe; but that they may not delude their owne ſoules, let them examine what was that which firſt ſet them on worke, whether it were Chriſt, or any by-ſelf-ends, as profit, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, &amp;c. let them conſider whether they could goe an end with the good work they have begun, if that profit, credit, &amp;c. faile there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from: Beloved, this will tell us the truth concerning our actions which we ſay are for Chriſt; to whom bring we forth? if to Chriſt, then he is our Maſter; but if to our ſelves, all we doe is voyd of goodneſſe and worth in his account, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.1.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, he that prizeth Chriſt above all, can and will part with all for him; this may ſeeme a riddle to a carnall heart, but the beleeving ſoule can both read it and doe it: That in <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.45, 46. makes it cleere: Every may that comes into the world is a Merchant for ſomething or other; ſome trade for profit, ſome for credit, others for pleaſure; and truly theſe three take up the imploymenss of all men before converſion, becauſe they know of no better commodities; but when a man is converted, his eyes are enlightned to ſee the vanity and emptineſſe of them, and the excellency of Chriſt, and thereupon he leaves off his old trade, and now trafiques onely for Chriſt, and for him he parts with all that cannot ſtand with him, or his having of him; his affections are tooke off from all things here below, and ſet on things above; Chriſt is all in all in his eye; and therefore if Chriſt will have his Husband, Wife, Iſaac, he ſhall; if Chriſt will have his Goods, his Liberty, yea, and life too, he ſhall, and he will thank Chriſt alſo for accepting of them; he will rejoyce (with the Apoſtles in <hi>Acts</hi> 5.41.) that he was accounted worthy to ſuffer for his Chriſt; ſo did the beleeving Hebrewes take the ſpoyling of their goods (for Chriſt) joyfully, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. Theſe are ſpoyling times, wherein hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily ſome of you here have ſuffered for Chriſt, and in the defence of his cauſe; how doe you take the plundering of your goods by ſea, or by land for Chriſt's ſake? doe you rejoyce at it, or doe you murmure and repine? is it a griefe and a vexation to you? then thou prizeſt thy goods above Chriſt, and haſt indeed no ſaving grace in thee.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:113188:20"/>
                  <p>Sixtly, he that prizeth Chriſt aright, highly eſteemes all that doth but ſmell of Chriſt; if any thing look but toward Chriſt, as having the leaſt relation to him, ſuch a ſoule will make exceeding much thereof: If any of you have a noble friend that you highly reverence and eſteeme, you will bid welcome and give free enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment to the meaneſt of his followers; ſo if you prize Chriſt as you ought, you wil not ſhut out of doors and that belongs to him, but in it ſhall come, and be bid heartily welcome for his Maſters ſake as well, yea more then for its owne; yet for its owne ſake too, becauſe ſuch a ſoule ſees an excellency in every thing that is Chriſts and hath a dependency on him; for as when a ſervant is bound Apprentice, his Maſter then diſcovers to him the myſtery of his trade, the worth and price of every commodity he deales in; ſo when a ſoule hath given up it ſelfe to Chriſt, he teacheth him the myſtery of godlineſſe, his trade, and the worth of every ſpirituall commodity, ſo that ſuch a ſoule knowes what a Sabbath is worth, what a Sacrament is worth, what a good Sermon is worth, what a poore Saint is worth, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. As for the Sabbath that will be a delight to ſuch a ſoule as prizeth Chriſt, and it will be honourable in his ſight becauſe it is Chriſt's day, and he loves it for Chriſt's ſakes becauſe it is a day of Chriſt's appearing to his holy ones; like as you ſee amongſt earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kings and Princes, they have their ſet feſtivall times wherein they ſhew themſelves to their people, beſtowing upon them great largeſſes, throwing among them plenty of gold and ſilver; ſo the King of Kings, and Lord of Lord hath his owne appointed day, which is now the firſt of the ſeven, which he hath ſet apart there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to manifeſt himſelfe to his choſen ones, and beſtow his grace on them in a more abundant meaſure, then at other times, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.13. ſuch a ſoule therefore as prizeth Chriſt, prizeth the Sabbath highly, becauſe he ſhall meet Chriſt then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe in his Ordinances: Truly Beloved, if any of you prize not the day of the Lord, you doe not prize the Lord of the day, neither have you any ſaving grace in you.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. The Word of Chriſt is very precious to ſuch a ſoule, for it is to him the lively picture of his Beloved; he is much in hearing and reading of it, becauſe of his love to Chriſt, who lies wrapt up therein; that he may conferre with his Chriſt, and behold the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113188:21"/>beauty of his Chriſt; when friends are parted, they love to hear of one another, and their Letters are much ſet by for that purpoſe; ſo the ſoule that accounteth Chriſt his beſt friend, loves to heare of Chriſt now in his abſence, and therefore he reads his Love-letter to him, peruſeth it often, for ſo Chriſt hath bid him to ſearch the Scriptures, becauſe they teſtifie of him; and as he loves to read Chriſt in his Word; ſo to heare Chriſt preached out of his Word; and truly he prizeth Chriſt preached more then Chriſt read, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is uſually more in the former then in the latter, more of the life, and light, and quickning power of Chriſt; and what hath moſt of Chriſt, hath moſt of this ſoules love, becauſe he loves and prizeth Chriſt moſt of all; is there any here that ſlights the reading or hearing of the Word of Chriſt, that ſoule prizeth not Chriſt;
<note place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note> for ſuch a ſoule as prizeth Chriſt, will delight therein, yea and to have it dwell richly in him, he looks at it, as a rich Word, becauſe his Pearle is treaſured up therein.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. The Sacraments are precious to him; each Sacrament is to him a rich Cabinet, becauſe his Jewell Chriſt crucified is in it: A Diamond is rich in it ſelfe, but when cut moſt precious; and ſo Chriſt moſt precious to a ſoule that hath ſaving grace, becauſe cut, and indeed cut with the ſenſe of his Fathers wrath for his ſake; truly he had beene of little price to us if not ſo cut; and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.2.</note> he was determined not to know any thing but Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified; marke, and him crucified, as if therein lay the excellency of Chriſt to a poore ſoule: Now his crucifying is lively repreſented in both Sacraments, and therefore the ſoule that prizeth Chriſt, prizeth both; he loves the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and to ſee it duly adminiſtred, becauſe it recals to him the benefit of ſhedding his blood, the waſhing away of his ſinnes: The Sacrament of his Supper he loves, becauſe therein he feeds on his Chriſt, and finding his daily want of ſuſtainance from him, his deſire is often to be at that ſpirituall Feaſt, according to Chriſt's direction of often receiving it by the hand of his Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. And indeed Chriſt at his departure hence, left this as a ſpeciall token of his love to be remembred of us thereby, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. which makes it the more precious to a ſoule that prizeth Chriſt above all, ſuch therefore as neglect and undervalue any of the Sacraments, deſpiſe Chriſt the Author and giver of them.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113188:21"/>
                  <p n="4">IV. Laſtly, the ſoule that prizeth Chriſt above all, prizeth the pooreſt man or worman who is rich in Chriſt; and good reaſon, for God himſelfe prizeth ſuch; doth not <hi>James</hi> ſay, hearken my beloved Brethren, <hi>hath not God choſen the poore of this world,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">James 2.5.</note> 
                     <hi>rich in faith? &amp;c.</hi> Now they that be rich in faith, are rich in Chriſt, for ſo much faith ſo much Chriſt; the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> reproves in the beginning of that chapter, the preferring of rich worldlings before poore chriſtians, which ſhewes you that ſaving grace prizeth the pooreſt ſoule that hath Chriſt before the greateſt King and Emperour, for ſuch a ſoule is heire to a greater Kingdome; is a precious Stone the worſe becauſe not ſet in Gold? is Chriſt this Jewell the leſſe worſe to thee becauſe wrapt up in a leatherne Jac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, or a threed-bare coat? Surely then thou judgeſt of Chriſt by the out-ſide, and judgeſt falſly of him, thou neither knoweſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> prizeſt him aright: Is there any here that prize and preferre i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their hearts and outward reſpects, the great rich men of this world more then a poore ſoule rich in Chriſt? that ſoule doth not priz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt as he ought; is there any here that delight more in the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; company of ſuch perſons as are dreſt up with gold Rings, ſilk Gowns, more then in Chriſt attired in a ruſſet coat? that ſoule pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth not Chriſt above all, neither hath ſaving grace in his heart.</p>
                  <p>A ſeventh rule of tryall of our prizing Chriſt above all is this a not-envying the men of this world, their abundance of Gold and Silver, houſes, lands, honours, preferments, and ſuch like knacks for to ſuch a ſoule as prizeth Chriſt above all, the world is crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and dead, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14. And he looks at the rich men as the heirs and executors thereof; and they indeed rejoyce and pride them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves much in their large Inventories, but a Chriſt-prizing ſoule pitties their poore and miſerable condition, which is comming on them, for when death comes, he ſtrips them of all; if their ſuppoſed riches take not their leave of them before (which many times they doe, by making themſelves wings) yet they can accompany them no farther then to the holes mouth,
<note place="margin">Prov. 23.5.</note> and then how naked are they in the ſight of this ſoul? who ſaith thus to himſelfe; <hi>Fret not at their prosperity for they ſhall ſoone be cut downe like the graſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.1.</note> 
                     <hi>and wither as the green hearb;</hi> they ſhall leave all behind them, but thou ſhalt carry thy treaſure, or rather thy treaſure and Treaſurer Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Job 1.21.</note> ſhall carry thee hence to a better place, to a place of eternall happineſſe,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113188:22"/>when they goe downe to the pit of endleſſe miſery.</p>
                  <p>Finally, the ſoule that prizeth above all, will ſtill be labouring to win others to Chriſt: Beloved, I pray mark the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a ſoule rich in Chriſt, and a man rich in this world: The rich worldling he would be rich alone, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.8. he would have all the world to himſelfe alone if he could; but he that is rich in Chriſt, would faine have others as rich as himſelfe; our Apoſtle's example makes it plaine, ſaying to <hi>Agrippa; I would to God not onely thou, but alſo all that heare me this day, were both almoſt and altogether ſuch as I am, except theſe bonds,</hi> Acts 26.29. Marke the large extent of his deſire in this kind, in two particulars: Firſt, he did wiſh all men this Chriſt of his; and ſecondly, as large a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Chriſt as he had himſelfe; every ſoule that prizeth Chriſt is ſtill motioning of him to others; he would make a match be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and his Wife, and ſhee between Chriſt and her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and both would faine hang this their Jewell on their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to adorne them in God's fight: They labour to kindle in their friends a love of Chriſt, and therefore in their company they are ſtill praiſing of Chriſt, and ſetting forth his excellencies; look you, ſay they, is not Chriſt a lovely Chriſt, the faireſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand? you never ſaw ſuch a beauty as his is; he is a loving Chriſt that will not ſee thee want, he will be tender over thee in all thy ſickneſſes and diſtreſſes, he will comfort thee at thy heart when none elſe can; he is a rich Chriſt, get him for thy Spouſe, and thou art provided for ever: Thus will ſuch a ſoule as prizeth Chriſt be wooing others to Chriſt; he would not goe to Heaven alone, for he knowes it is not there as it is here; but there as the more the merrier, ſo the beteer cheere too; and that he ſhall not have the leſſe, but the more, by bringing in others to be ſharers with him in his Chriſt; Chriſt multiplies to ſuch a ſoule as thus divides him to others; and therefore the ſoule that prizeth Chriſt, labours all he can to draw other unto Chriſt; and beſide, he knowes it is an honour to Chriſt to have many ſervants attending him, and this prevailes exceedingly with the ſoule which doth all to the glory of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Thus having finiſhed the tryall of the firſt part of the Queſtion in hand, whether we prize Chriſt above all things, we come to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113188:22"/>
                  <p>The ſecond part, whether we prize Chriſt above all both for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification and Sanctification.</p>
                  <p>Firſt for Juſtification, and for this take theſe two Rules.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, examine thine owne heart, whether thou thinkeſt thy perſon is accepted in God's ſight for thy performances, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they prevaile in thy account with God, to prize thee more then others: Thus did the proud Phariſee conceive, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was ſo bold as to thank God that he was not as this man, the poore Publican; but a ſoule that prizeth Chriſt-above all, looks at all thoſe Phariſaicall Robes of legall righteouſneſſe in this point but as ragges, yea as filthy ragges, and therefore he puls them over his ears, and by no meanes would be found of God in them; onely Chriſt's righteouſneſſe is the Robe that he would have to goe in before God: He looks at the Lord Jeſus as the onely Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that can pleaſe God's ſight, and therefore he labours every day to put him on more and more; if therefore thou prideſt thy ſelfe in, and deckeſt thy ſelfe up with thine owne righteouſneſſe, thou prizeſt not Chriſt at all for Juſtification.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, aske thine owne heart what opinion it hath of thy good works, in procuring thy pardon from God's Juſtice: if they be thy gaine, then Chriſt is loſſe to thee; if thou thinkeſt, with the Papiſt, to merit and gaine Heaven, or the leaſt part of Heaven by them, Chriſt is nothing worth to thee: I know the Papiſts ſay, they exclude not Chriſt by including their works in matter of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification; but what they ſay not, that they doe; for by their making of works to be ſharers with Chriſt, they doe really exclude Chriſt, and ſo themſelves from Juſtification: If you cry up works in Juſtification, you cry downe Chriſt; the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in our Text prizing Chriſt above all for Juſtification, beats downe works to the ground; for indeed therein Chriſt muſt be alone all in all, or elſe nothing at all; as all ſound and learned Proteſtants have and doe continually maintaine againſt the Popiſh Doctrine of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and therefore I ſhall not need to inſiſt any further on this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is more neceſſary for us who take that for granted among us, but little think of this latter, which yet is as neceſſary to be knowne and learned as the former, as hath been proved: and whether we have learned to prize Chriſt above all for Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113188:23"/>if we deale truly with our owne ſoules, we may know by theſe Rules of examination.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, ſee how thine heart ſtands affected with the diſhonour of Chriſt; is Chriſt's diſgrace and loſſe more to thee then thine own? for what we deſire moſt, we ſhall grieve moſt for, if we fall ſhort thereof; never was Chriſt more diſhonoured by his own people then in theſe times, both in private and publike; in families, in churches and Kingdomes; feele therefore the pulſe of thy ſoule, in theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed times, wherein the world ſeemes to draw nigh apace unto its end; Chriſt is diſhonoured in thy family, this church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and how doeſt thou take it? doeſt thou not ſee his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell neglected, yea oppoſed? are not his Sacraments even by ſuch as goe for his ſervants, caſt behind their backs, and laid aſide as of no uſe? are not his Sabbaths prophaned, his Name blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed, his ſervants abuſed, and many more horrid indignities put on him? and how takeſt thou it to heart? It may be thou wilt ſay, it doth much break your heart to ſee things ſo much diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but be adviſed here, that you may not be miſtaken in your griefe, ſee whether it be not more for thy ſelfe, then for Chriſt's ſake; now thou ſeeſt the ſhip of the State crackt, and ſinking to a ſhip-wrack, yea and Church too, by the many rents in it (if the Lord ſave not both) it may well be thought that thou art deeply affected; but I pray weigh the matter throughly in your own ſoul; is it not becauſe thou art a paſſenger therein, and thou haſt a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in this Barke that is ſplit, and thou knoweſt if that ſink thou canſt not eſcape, but thou and all that is thine muſt be quite loſt, and therefore thou ſetteſt thy hand to help ſave the Barke, that thou and thine may be ſaved therein? But if thou wert out of the ſhip and embarqued in another Kingdome and church with all thy venture, wouldſt thou be ſo much troubled for the loſſe of Chriſt's Veſſell here? would it come ſo neer to thy heart then, to heare of all the diſhonour that Chriſt ſuffers, by broaching of Errours and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, to the great impeachment of his truth, and by the great diſſention between his beſt ſervants? Then it is a ſigne thou pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeſt Chriſt above all in Sanctification; for a ſoule that doth ſo, ſeeks to advance Chriſt's glory moſt of all, and that Chriſt may be more and more ſerved by him and all others.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, conſider how thy heart ſtandeth affected towards ſin: If
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113188:23"/>thou ſeek Chriſt above all for holineſſe thou wilt be at utter emni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the greateſt enemy thereto, and that is ſinne; every ſinne, even thy boſome-ſin, thy darling-ſin will become as odious to thee as the fouleſt Toad; neither wilt thou be at defiance onely with outward actuall ſinnes, but alſo with thoſe that are more hidden and inward; the ſinnes of thy nature; yea, and truly theſe will be moſt offenſive to thee, becauſe they are as fountaines of iniquity, and roots of bitterneſſe in thee; thus we find <hi>David</hi> more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of his naughty and corrupt heart, then of his actuall tranſgreſſions of murther, adultery, drunkenneſſe and idleneſſe; and <hi>Paul</hi> cryes out of the body of death in him, Rom. 7. a ſoul that ſeeks Chriſt for Sanctification, would digge up ſinne by the roots, another man may top and lop luſt in the branches thereof: try therefore your ſelves by this rule.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, examine your ſelves what entertainment the doctrine of walking exactly and preciſely finds with your hearts; truly if you ſeek Chriſt above all for holineſſe, you will prize his ſtricteſt lawes at the higheſt rate; if Chriſt's Commandements be grievous to thee, and thou wouldeſt caſt off his lawes as bonds with them in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. thou haſt no eſteem of Chriſt at all for Sanctification. His Yoake is light and eaſie to ſuch as ſeeke Chriſt for holineſſe.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, he that prizeth Chriſt above all for Sanctification, doth not only prize his ſtricteſt commands, but alſo practice them; he loves to walk in the ſtricteſt way his beſt Beloved hath chalked out to him; bring therefore your lives and converſations and lay them to that rule in <hi>Titus</hi> 2.12. doe you deny ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts? doe you live godly, righteouſly and ſoberly in this preſent world? is this your endeavour to give both God and man his due, and to keep your ſelves from being overcharged with ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting and drunkenneſſe, and the cares of this life? Then thou doeſt ſeek Chriſt for holineſſe; for ſuch a ſoules deſire is to walk altogether in the wayes of holineſſe, doing of duty in a newneſſe of life is all its delight; and why? becauſe this is the readieſt way to grow up in holineſſe, and to become more and more like to Chriſt, whom he deſires above all for this very purpoſe, that he might be perfect in holineſſe.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, take a ſcantling of your Humiliations, Faſtings and Prayers, and thereby you may judge of your ſelves concerning
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113188:24"/>your eſtimation of Chriſt for holineſſe; we have faſted and prayed often, humbled our ſelves publikely and privately many times, once a moneth at the leaſt, for the ſpace of three yeers almoſt; but let us try wherefore we have been ſo often in humiliation, faſting and prayer, what hath been the firſt wheel that hath moved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: Have we ſought Chriſt for our Sanctification in all our Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes? what bottome hath our ſorrow ſtood upon? no other ground but the ſenſe of God's wrath, a feare of that great judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſword, deſtruction here, and damnation hereafter? truly if our humiliation hath ſprung from no other cauſe then this we have not prized Chriſt above all for our Sanctification; for if holineſſe (whereby we might ſerve God better then we doe) were our aime, when we faſt and pray and humble our ſelves, our ſinnes and corruptions, not our afflictions, move us firſt thereto. Indeed judgements and corrections are inſtructions, they open our eyes to ſee our errours, and then a love of holineſſe brings us on our knees for our ſinnes, to beg a pardon for them, and a cleanſing of them; ſaving grace teacheth a ſoul to begin at the right end of his work; he that thinks to take judgement away before his ſinne, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faſteth and prayeth, he begins at the wrong end of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; he muſt take away the cauſe and then the effect will follow of it ſelfe; dig up ſinne by the root, and that bitter fruit of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which growes on its branches will wither and come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; to humble, faſt and pray, and doe ſuch like duties for no other end but out of a deſire of peace, which we want, and to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the plagues we have deſerved, is onely to prize Chriſt above all for Juſtification, whereby we are diſcharged and acquitted from the guilt of our offences, and conſequently from the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due to us for the ſame; but to humble our ſelves out of ſenſe of our ſinnes, the filthineſſe of them, their magnitude, multitude and power; and we begge Chriſt that he may come and reigne in the midſt of his and our enemies that are in us, that he would waſh and cleanſe us, waſh our feet, hands, head and all over, that we might doe his ſervice more decently and in order, as becomes his ſervants, then we prize Chriſt for Sanctification: And truly it is to be feared, that we have not humbled, faſted and prayed in this kind, becauſe the Lord hath not heard and anſwered all this while, it ſeems more probable we have ſought the Lord onely in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113188:24"/>way, for benefit by him, out of meere ſelf-love, and therefore we have been deſpiſed as ſelf-ſeekers; the Lord hath ſeen we have brought forth all unto our ſelves, and therefore he hath made all returne empty and vaine to us: we ſhall never find Chriſt juſtifying us, till we deſire him ſanctifying us: the Lord gives his Chriſt not onely to ſave a ſoule, but alſo that the ſoule may by Chriſt ſerve him; indeed the Lord may give peace, plenty, and ſuch like out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things he may heap on wicked men, but there is no Chriſt in them, and therefore they more hurt then do good to them, yea and the Word doe with them more evill then good; but to a ſoule that hath ſaving grace, and prizeth Chriſt above all for holineſſe, the Lord give him Chriſt in all his gifts and tokens, of what kind ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be; whether of his left or of his right hand, and therefore they all doe him good, he is the better and not the worſe for them, yea and he makes a good uſe of them, to the glory of God and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of others; wherefore (to turne this ſigne into a motive) as we would obtaine our deſire, and ſee peace and truth ſetled amongſt us, and as we would have good and no hurt by them, when they come, let us learne in all our Humiliations, Faſtings, Prayers, and all duty to prize and ſeek Chriſt above all for ſanctification, that is, that we may not onely lead a quiet and a peaceable life,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2, 3.</note> but alſo that we live in all godlineſſe and honeſty, for this indeed is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>Let me conclude with a word of reproofe of all ſuch as doe not prize Chriſt above all for ſanctification ſo well as for juſtification; theſe perſons have no ſaving grace in them, and no true love to Chriſt; they love happineſſe, but care not for holineſſe; ſo they could be ſaved by Chriſt, let who will ſerve Chriſt for them; they have all their deſire, and ſo no more need of Chriſt: Ah, let ſuch poore ſoules take heed of their King; there is more need of Chriſt in juſtification then ſanctification: Truly Beloved, it is one of the devil's maſter-pieces in theſe times, to take men off from ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to cry up free grace onely in juſtification; when as there is as great if not greater free grace, and therefore a greater need of it in ſanctification then in juſtification, as hath been ſhewne: ſuch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as ſeek not Chriſt above all for holineſſe as well as happineſſe are juſtly to be blamed.</p>
               <p>What blame then are they worthy of who deſire Chriſt to be a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113188:25"/>cloke of their unholineſſe? beleeve me, a Church-Proteſtant is worſe then a Church-Papiſt; doe you not ſee what bribers they are? ſee how they bribe their owne conſciences and their brethrens eyes with an out-ſide of Chriſt; mark you not how they be at a ſee with prayer, hearing of Sermons, repetitions, &amp;c. that they may keep a boſome-ſinne? Are there not many Proteſtants (I could wiſh there were none here) that weare a gliſtering garment of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion uppermoſt, as if they had put on that glorious Diadem the Lord Jeſus? Put alas! that ſoule which hath put on Chriſt indeed is all glorious within; the faireſt part of its beauty is in the heart; this ſoul hath a better in-ſide then out-ſide; there is no true judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be given of him by his outward appearance; and the truth is, ſuch a man is moſt carefull about his heart, to adorn that, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove that to God: But ſuch as have not truly put on Chriſt, all their care is to trick and trim up their outward man, their viſible out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide; they put the beſt ſide outmoſt: How many under their brave coverſluts, wear next to their hearts garments naſty both for courſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; foulneſſe; doth not this man put on covetouſneſſe? that man envy? another malice? a fourth hypocriſie? &amp;c. doe theſe ſerve Chriſt in any of their performances? nothing leſſe; they ſerve o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly themſelves by him; they doe but make him their ſhooing-horne to pull on their ſelf-ends; ſo long as Chriſt goes their way, he ſhall have their company, yea ſo long as the chariot of ſelf-love laſteth, they will march as furiouſly for Chriſt, as <hi>Jehn</hi> did for <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah,</hi> Baal ſhall downe, and all his Prieſts too; but if ſelfe and Chriſt come in competition, and ſo muſt part, then farewell Chriſt; theſe mens way now lyes quite contrary to Chriſt's; and let them goe, they are not worthy the ſociety of a chriſtian that thus ſlight and abuſe Chriſt, whom <hi>Paul</hi> and every poore ſoule that hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace doth prize Chriſt above all both for Juſtification and Sanctification.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>I have peruſed this Sermon on Phil. <hi>3.7, 8,</hi> &amp;c. and finding it to be very godly, judicious and profitable, I doe allow it to be printed and publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Downame.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
